Guide to the Daughters of the American Revolution. Bitter Root Chapter (Missoula, Mont.) Records 1880-2019
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Daughters of the American Revolution. Bitter Root Chapter (Missoula, Mont.) Records
1880-2017
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 013
Daughters of the American Revolution. Bitter Root Chapter (Missoula, Mont.)
9.25 linear feet
The Bitter Root Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution was organized in 1919. The collection includes meeting minutes, clippings about chapter activities, scrapbooks, and historical records relating to Montana and the Bitter Root Valley.
Historical Note
Daughters of the American Revolution (DAR) is a women's organization with three objectives: historical preservation, educational pursuits, and patriotic endeavors. The DAR image is one of service to home, country, and God. DAR works to preserve the heritage of the United States through historic tours, restorations and markers, museums, and genealogical research. They emphasize education through citizenship classes, youth development, programs and announcements on TV and radio, DAR-approved schools, student scholarship and loan funds, and patriotic publications. To be a member, one must be at least eighteen years of age and in direct lineal descent of a man or woman who served in the armed forces or as a civil officer in one of the colonies or states, was a recognized patriot, or was an individual who gave material aid in the fight for American independence. The Montana state society DAR began in 1894, and the Bitter Root chapter, which formed the bulk of this collection, organized in 1919 with twelve charter members.
The collection contains meeting minutes, scrapbooks, and genealogical records from the Bitter Root Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution.
The collection is divided into ten series:
Series I: Meeting Minutes, 17 folders, 1919-2015
Series II: Procedures, 2 folders, 1919-2012
Series III: Correspondence, 1 folder, 1940-1980
Series IV: Newspaper Clippings, 16 folders, 1912-1995
Series V: History, Genealogy, and Related Materials, 28 folders, 1880-2019
Series VI: State Society Daughters of the American Revolution, 4 folders, 1894-1999
Series VII: National Society Daughters of the American Revolution, 3 folders, 1939-1991
Series VIII: Yearbooks, 4 folders, 1929-2000
Series IX: Scrapbooks, 4.5 linear feet, 1952-2017
Series X: Financial Ledger, 1 ledger, 1949-1989
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and the University of Montana-Missoula.
Gift of Mrs. H.W. Gregory, 1974. Gift of the Bitter Root Chapter of the DAR, 2008, 2009, 2011, 2012, 2015 and 2019.
Patriotic societies--Montana--Missoula; Women--Montana--Missoula--Societies and clubs
United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--Societies, etc.
Daughters of the American Revolution; Daughters of the American Revolution. Montana State Society
Montana; Women
- Meeting Minutes, 1919-2015; Series I; 17 folders
  This series includes minutes to Bitter Root chapter general meetings and board meetings. Member attendance sheets, monthly and yearly treasurer reports, and newspaper clippings are also included.
  - 1919-1923 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 1923-1930 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - 1930-1934 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - 1934-1941 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - 1941-1947 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - 1941-1949 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - 1960-1967 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - 1967-1973 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - 1973-1975 (Box-folder 2/1)
  - 1975-1979 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - January 1979-June 1979 (Box-folder 2/3)
  - 1985-1987 (Box-folder 2/4)
  - 1990-1999 (Box-folder 2/5)
  - 2000-2002 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - 2007-2009 (Box-folder 13/1)
  - 2009-2012 (Box-folder 13/2)
  - 2012-2015 (Box-folder 13/3)
- Procedures, 1919-2012; Series II; 2 folders
  This series contains chapter by-laws, monthly and yearly treasurer's reports, meeting rituals, duties of DAR secretaries, presentations, National Defense Committee report, a blank letterhead, as well as an exhaustive list of Bitter Root chapter DAR members.
  - 1919-1957 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - 1995-2012 (Box-folder 2/8)
- Correspondence, 1940-1980; Series III; 1 folder
  Included are thank you, membership and resignation letters, letters from national and state committees, Albert L. Stone, and Elers Koch, and letters regarding the DAR Outstanding Home Economics Award and the Deaf Citizens of Montana.
  - 1940-1980 (Box-folder 2/9)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1912-1995; Series IV; 16 folders
  This series includes newspaper clippings pertaining to the history of Missoula, the Bitter Root valley and Montana, and photos of Montana governors 1864 to 1925. Also included are articles about chapter meetings, activities, guest speakers, state convention, award winners, and editorials on behalf of DAR. This series also includes Press Books that were compiled by the DAR.
  - 1912-1944 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - 1925-1974 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - 1929-1937 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - 1936-1955 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 2/15)
  - 1987-1988 (Box-folder 2/16)
  - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 2/17)
  - 1989-1990 (Box-folder 2/18)
  - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - 1991-1992 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - 1992-1993 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - 1994-1995 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - 1995-1996 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - March 1995 (Box-folder 3/7)
- History, Genealogy, and Related Materials, 1880-2019; Series V; 28 folders
  This series contains papers on numerous historical subjects relating to western Montana, including excerpts from the January 1, 1892 Missoula Gazette, church and mission histories, church records of baptisms, burials, and marriages, the history of the Missoula Library, Missoula, Missoula County and the Bitter Root valley, the history of the Bitter Root chapter DAR, historical landmarks, tombstone inscriptions, the early history of the Forest Service, biographies of Franklin Hargraves Woody, Hiram Knowles, John B. Catlin, De Loss Smith, Francis Dean Brown, and James Walsh, the history of the As You Like It Club and of the first president of Montana State University.
  - Montana and Missoula History, 1880-1946 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - University and Organizational Histories, 1939-1942 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Personal Histories, 1943 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Church Records and Tombstone Inscriptions, 1871-1943 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Genealogy, 1755-1821 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Genealogy, 1755-1906 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Genealogy, 1760-1890 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Genealogy, 1762-1934 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Genealogy, 1806-1941 (Box-folder 3/16)
  - Genealogy, 1808-1940 (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Genealogy, 1811-1980 (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Genealogy, 1840-1977 (Box-folder 4/3)
  - Genealogy, 1848-1964 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Genealogy, 1850-1969 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Genealogy, 1876-1928 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Genealogy, 1859-1984 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Genealogical Records, 1883-1892 (Box-folder 4/8)
  - Genealogy, 1887-1942 (Box-folder 4/9)
  - Genealogical Records, 1889-1892 (Box-folder 4/10)
  - Genealogical Records, 1892-1902 (Box-folder 4/11)
  - Genealogy, 1892-1990 (Box-folder 4/12)
  - Genealogical Records, 1893-1895 (Box-folder 4/13)
  - Genealogical Records, 1897-1901 (Box-folder 4/14)
  - Genealogy, 1900-1988 (Box-folder 4/15)
  - Montana State Society Daughters of the American Revolution History, Bitter Root Chapter, 1894-1984 (Box-folder 13/4)
  - Update to the Montana State Centennial History Daughters of the American Revolution Volume 5, 1894-2008 (Box-folder 13/5)
  - Bitter Root Chapter the First One Hundred Years, 2019 (Box-folder 15/1)
  - 125 Years of Service to Montana, Publication, 2019 (Box-folder 15/2)
- State Society Daughters of the American Revolution, 1894-1999; Series VI; 7 folders
  Included are state by-laws, dues, correspondence, conference programs, scholarship fund materials, and a history of the state society, comprised of biographies of state regents, state chapter histories of all seventeen chapters, history of the student loan and scholarship fund and historic markers, and a comprehensive membership roll.
  - By-laws and Correspondence, 1942-1961 (Box-folder 5/1)
  - State Conference, 1973 (Box-folder 5/2)
  - State Conference Programs, 1925-1999 (Box-folder 5/3)
  - State Society DAR history, 1894-1960 (Box-folder 5/4)
  - State Centennial History, 1894-1994 (Box-folder 5/5)
  - State History, 1970-1980, undated (Box-folder 5/6)
  - Montana Scholarship Fund, 1924-1958 (Box-folder 5/7)
- National Society Daughters of the American Revolution, 1939-1991; Series VII; 2 folders
  This series contains publications of the National Defense Committee, National Defense through Patriotic Education Committee, and DAR-approved schools.
  - Publications, 1939-1963 (Box-folder 5/8)
  - Publications, 1985-1991 (Box-folder 5/9)
- Year Books, 1929-2000; Series VIII
  Year Books include membership and event information.
  - Year Books, 1929-1949 (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Year Books, 1949-1969 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Year Books, 1969-1989 (Box-folder 6/3)
  - Year Books, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 6/4)
- Scrapbooks, 1952-2017; Series IX; 4.5 linear feet
  Scrapbooks typically include photographs, programs, correspondence and newspaper clippings.
  - 1947-1973 (Box-folder OS 1)
  - 1952-1954 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - 1973-1981 (Box-folder OS 2)
  - 1981-1983 (Box-folder OS 2)
  - 1985-1986 (Box-folder 6/6)
  - 1986-1987 (Box-folder 7/1)
  - 1987-1989 (Box-folder 7/2)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 7/3)
  - 1989 (Box-folder 7/4)
  - 1989 (Box-folder 8/1)
  - 1990-1991 (Box-folder 8/2)
  - 1990-1994 (Box-folder 8/3)
  - 1991-1992 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - 1992-1994 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - 1994 (Box-folder OS 2)
  - 1994-1996 (Box-folder 9/3)
  - 1996-1998 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - 1998-2000 (Box-folder 10/2)
  - 2000-2002 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - 2002-2003 (Box-folder 11/1)
  - 2003-2004 (Box-folder 11/2)
  - 2004-2005 (Box-folder 11/3)
  - 2005-2006 (Box-folder 11/4)
  - 2006-2008 (Box-folder OS 3)
  - 2008-2010 (Box-folder OS 4)
  - 2010-2011 (Box-folder OS 4)
  - 2013-2014 (Box-folder 13/6)
  - 2014-2015 (Box-folder 14/1)
  - 2015-2016 (Box-folder 14/2)
  - 2016-2017 (Box-folder 14/3)
- Financial Ledger, 1949-1989; Series X
  Ledger book documenting membership payments and chapter income and expenses.
  - Financial Ledger, 1949-1989 (Box 12)